Guide to the Consumer Reports. A.J. Isserman papers, 1917-1974 and undated RL.11778
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. A.J. Isserman papers
1917-1974 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11778
1.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Abraham J. Isserman was a labor lawyer, counsel to the American Civil Liberties Union during the 1930s, and one of the original members of the Board of Directors of Consumers Union. The Consumer Reports A.J. Isserman papers includes correspondence, clippings, court briefs and depositions, book manuscript drafts, photographs and other printed materials relating to Isserman's work in civil rights and labor law. Topics include labor union activities and strikes, civil liberties, communist influence, investigations into Un-American activities, deportation, and disbarment of lawyers. Persons and institutions reflected in the collection include the American Civil Liberties Union of New Jersey, the Dies Committee, Judge Harold Medina, and Leinhard Bergel. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Personal and Professional Files; Disbarment and Reinstatement
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Abraham J. Isserman was a labor lawyer, counsel to the American Civil Liberties Union during the 1930s, and one of the original members of the Board of Directors of Consumers Union.
Abraham J. Isserman was born in 1900 in Belgium. Isserman served with the Royal Fusiliers during World War I. Isserman served as Counsel to ACLU 1930s-1941 and as defense counsel for strikers at Consumers Research who were fired during the 1935 strike. Isserman was a member of the Consumers Union Board of Directors from 1936. Isserman was part of the defense counsel during the Foley Square trial of 1949, in the course of which Isserman was disbarred in 1952, and later reinstated in 1961. Isserman was a partner in the Isserman and Isserman legal firm. Isserman died in 1988 in New York.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. A.J. Isserman papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Advertising Council records
African American history marketing and promotional posters
J. Walter Thompson Company. Edward G. Wilson papers
Paula Green papers
Collection Overview
The Consumer Reports A.J. Isserman papers include correspondence, clippings, court briefs and depositions, book manuscript drafts, photographs and other printed materials relating to Isserman's work in civil rights and labor law. Topics include labor union activities and strikes, civil liberties, communist influence, investigations into Un-American activities, deportation, and disbarment of lawyers. Persons and institutions reflected in the collection include the American Civil Liberties Union of New Jersey, the Dies Committee, Judge Harold Medina, and Leinhard Bergel. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Civil rights; Labor unions; Lawyers -- Political activity; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; American Civil Liberties Union -- History; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities
- Personal and Professional Files, 1917-1974 and undated; 1
  - Book files--Notes, drafts, introduction, 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Civil liberties clippings, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 1)
  - Crisis in the Civil Liberties Union, 1940 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Pamphlet relating to the debate within the ACLU, beginning around 1939, between its traditional mission of nonpartisan protection of speech rights and a growing sentiment to oppose anti-democratic doctrines such as fascism and Nazism.
  - Edith Beckman deportation case, 1931-1932 (Box 3)
    Edith Beckman was an organizer with the National Textile Workers Union, arrested in October 1931 and held for deportation until released under bond in November 1932. File contains clippings related to the case, Supreme Court Justice Louis Brandeis intervention, Beckman's hunger strike and eventual release.
  - Harvard lecture (notes), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Investigating Committees and Civil Rights (National Federation for Constitutional Liberties), 1941 (Box 1)
  - Lawyer Troubles in Political Trials (Fowler Harper and David Haber, Yale Law Review), 1951 (Box 1)
  - Leinhard Bergel case, 1935-1965 (Box 1)
    Leinhard Bergel, professor in the German Department at Rutgers University and an outspoken opponent of Nazism, was dismissed from his position in 1935. Bergel claimed that the department head, Friedrich Hauptman, who was pro-Nazi, fired him on ideological grounds. Rutgers upheld the dismissal. In 1940-1941, Hauptman returned to Germany and joined the Nazi party. He was arrested after the war on suspicion of spying for Germany, but apparently not tried and died in Austria in 1978. Bergel became professor of comparative litarature at CUNY and died in 1987.
  - Leinhard Bergel case, 1935, 1965; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Memorandum on the Power of Congressional Investigating Committee, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 1)
  - New Jersey Civil Liberties Union, 1934-1937 (Box 3)
  - New Jersey injunction/picket rule, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Princeton--ACLU collection notes, 1932-1965 (Box 1)
    Isserman's library search notes; includes Memorandum for American Bar Association re. Interference with attorneys in professional duties (1932)
  - Program for the elderly (housing), 1974 (Box 1)
  - Royal Fusiliers--Documentation and photographs, approximately 1917 (Box 1)
  - Supporting materials (sit-down strikes, etc.), 1936-1971 (Box 1)
  - Un-American activities (Dies Committee), 1937-1940 (Box 1)
    Dies Committee, named for Texas Representative Martin Dies, precursor to the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC)
  - Un-American activities (Dies Committee), 1938 (Box 3)
- Disbarment and Reinstatement, 1949-1965; 2
  - General, 1949-1961; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1950-1961 (Box 3)
  - Due Process in a Political Trial (National Non-Partisan Committee to Defend the Rights of the 12 Communist Leaders), approximately 1949 (Box 1)
  - Judge Harold Medina, 1949-1961 (Box 1)
    Harold J. Medina (1888-1990) presided over the Foley Square Trial. Charged Isserman and the legal defense team of contempt of court.
  - Judge Harold Medina, 1950-1965 (Box 3)
  - Supreme Court of New Jersey, 1959 (Box 1)
    Petition that led to Isserman's reinstatement to the Bar, in 1961.
  - Supreme Court of the United States, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    Appeals in the Foley Square trial.
  - U.S. Court of Appeals--Appellate brief, approximately 1952 (Box 2)